A Guide to the Virginia Secretary of the Commonwealth executive papers, 1866-1878
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Secretary of the Commonwealth executive papers, 1866-1878
The Library of Virginia
21569
7.2 cubic feet (16 boxes)
Virginia. Secretary of the Commonwealth
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred by the Virginia Secretary of the Commonwealth, 18 May 1939.
Historical Information
The Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth has evolved from early colonial times when there existed a Secretary of the Colony. Thomas Nelson held the position of the first Secretary of Virginia in 1776. Early Secretaries were elected by the public. An Act of the General Assembly in 1920 changed the election to a joint vote of the General Assembly. In a 1930 Act the duties of the Secretary were redefined with the Secretary of the Commonwealth serving as the ex officio secretary of the Governor, as custodian of many official State records, and as keeper of the Greater and Lesser Seals of the Commonwealth. The office of the Secretary has gradually acquired other functions, such as: service of out-of-state civil process; appointment and regulation of notaries public; and registration and oversight of lobbyists. The Office became a gubernational appointment subsequent to a 1958 Act of the Assembly. The Secretary of the Commonwealth is under the jurisdiction of the Governor's Office.
Scope and Content
Contains a variety of material mostly sent to the Secretary of the Commonwealth from citizens and other government entities. The records include applications for government employment and service, correspondence related to job inquiries, Eastern Lunatic Asylum, and the disaster at the capitol building in 1870, loyalty oaths for state and local officials, opinions of the Attorney General, petitions for pardons, receipts, recommendations for jobs, reports of the State Penitentiary, and formal resignations. The bulk of the records are applications for government positions such as those for inspectors, public guard members, notaries, magistrates, commissioners, and board members.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of record.
Contents List
- Series I. Executive papers, 1866-1878.
  - Applications
    - Cattle, Weigher of (State Weigh Master), 1869-1870. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Cattle, Weigher of (State Weigh Master), 1870. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Cattle, Weigher of (State Weigh Master), 1870. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Cattle, Weigher of (State Weigh Master), 1870. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Constables and Magistrates (Accomack - Amelia), 1870. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Constables and Magistrates (Amherst - Botetourt), 1870. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Constables and Magistrates (Brunswick - Charlotte), 1870. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Constables and Magistrates (Chesterfield - Cumberland), 1870. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Constables and Magistrates (Danville - Fauquier), 1870. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Constables and Magistrates (Fluvanna - Goochland), 1870. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Constables and Magistrates (Greensville - Henrico), 1870. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Constables and Magistrates (Henry - Lancaster), 1870. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Constables and Magistrates (Lee - Montgomery), 1870. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Constables and Magistrates (Nelson - Prince Edward), 1870. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Constables and Magistrates (Prince William - Warren), 1870. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Curator, Hampton Normal and Agricultural Institute, 1872-1873. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Deeds, Commissioner of, 1869-1870. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Deeds, Commissioner of, 1870. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Deeds, Commissioner of, 1871. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Deeds, Commissioner of, 1871. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Deeds, Commissioner of, 1871-1872. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Deeds, Commissioner of, 1872; undated. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Flour, Inspector of (Alexandria), 1870-1871. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Flour, Inspector of (Alexandria), 1871-1874. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Flour, Inspector of (Chesterfield), 1870-1871. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Flour, Inspector of (Culpeper), 1874. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Flour, Inspector of (Farmville), 1872. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Flour, Inspector of (Harrisonburg), 1870-1871. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Flour, Inspector of (Lynchburg), undated. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Flour, Inspector of (Norfolk City), 1869-1870. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Flour, Inspector of (Norfolk City), 1870-1873. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Flour, Inspector of (Petersburg), 1869-1871. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Flour, Inspector of (Petersburg), 1874. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Flour, Inspector of (Petersburg), 1874. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Flour, Inspector of (Portsmouth), 1870-1874. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Flour, Inspector of (Richmond City), 1869-1870. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Flour, Inspector of (Richmond City), 1870-1872. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Flour, Inspector of (Richmond City), 1873. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Flour, Inspector of (Richmond City), 1874. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Flour, Inspector of (Richmond City), 1874. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Flour, Inspector of (Scottsville), 1870. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Flour, Inspector of (Staunton), 1870. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Guano, Inspector of (Petersburg), 1870. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Guano, Inspector of (Richmond City), 1869-1870. (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Immigration agent (foreign applications), 1871-1873. (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Immigration agent (U.S. citizen applications), 1870-1872. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Immigration agent (miscellaneous applications), 1872-1873. (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Lime, Inspector of, 1870. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Lumber, Inspector of (Alexandria), 1870. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Lumber, Inspector of (Norfolk City), 1869-1870. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Lumber, Inspector of (Norfolk City), 1870. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Lumber, Inspector of (Norfolk City), 1871-1873. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Lumber, Inspector of (Norfolk City), 1873. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Lumber, Inspector of (Portsmouth), 1869-1870. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Lumber, Inspector of (Portsmouth), 1870-1873. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Notary Public, 1870. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Notary Public, 1870; undated. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Protection and Propagation of Fish, Commissioner of, 1871. (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Provisions, Inspector of, 1873-1874. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Public Guard, 1866-1869. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Public Guard, 1870. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Public Guard, 1870. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Public Guard, 1870. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Public Guard, 1870. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Public Guard, 1870. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Public Guard, 1870-1871; undated. (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Schools, Superintendent of, 1870-1872. (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Schools, Superintendent of, 1873; undated. (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Tar pitch, Inspector of, 1870. (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Tobacco, Inspector of (Farmville), 1869. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Tobacco, Inspector of (Farmville), 1869-1878. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Tobacco, Inspector of (Lynchburg), 1870. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Tobacco, Inspector of (Lynchburg), 1870. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Tobacco, Inspector of (Lynchburg), 1870. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Tobacco, Inspector of (Lynchburg), 1870. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Tobacco, Inspector of (Lynchburg), 1870-1871; undated. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Tobacco, Inspector of (Petersburg), 1870. (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Tobacco, Inspector of (Petersburg), 1870-1871. (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Tobacco, Inspector of (Petersburg), 1871-1874. (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Tobacco, Inspector of (Petersburg), 1874. (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Tobacco, Inspector of (Petersburg), 1874. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Tobacco, Inspector of (Petersburg), 1874; undated. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Tobacco, Inspector of (Richmond City), 1869-1870. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Tobacco, Inspector of (Richmond City), 1870. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Tobacco, Inspector of (Richmond City), 1870-1872. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Tobacco, Inspector of (Richmond City), 1873-1874. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Tobacco, Inspector of (Richmond City), 1874. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Tobacco, Inspector of (Richmond City), 1874. (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Tobacco, Inspector of (Richmond City), 1874. (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Tobacco, Inspector of (Richmond City), 1875-1876; undated. (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Tobacco, Inspector of (miscellaneous localities), 1869-1874. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Vaccine agent, 1869-1870. (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Vaccine agent, 1870; undated. (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Visitors, Board of (Insitution for the Deaf, Dumb and Blind, Staunton), 1870-1873; undated. (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Visitors, Board of (Medical College of Virginia), 1871; undated. (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Visitors, Board of (Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College), 1873. (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Various positions, 1868-1869. (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Various positions, 1869. (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Various positions, 1870. (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Various positions, 1870. (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Various positions, 1870. (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Various positions, 1870. (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Various positions, 1870. (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Various positions, 1870-1871. (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Various positions, 1872; undated. (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence
    - Books and journals, Ordering of, 1870-1871. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Books and journals, Ordering of, 1872. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Books and journals, Ordering of, 1872; undated. (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Capitol disaster, 1870. (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Capitol disaster, 1870. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Eastern Lunatic Asylum, 1869-1870. (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Eastern Lunatic Asylum, 1870. (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Eastern Lunatic Asylum, 1870. (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Eastern Lunatic Asylum, 1871-1872. (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Eastern Lunatic Asylum, 1872. (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Eastern Lunatic Asylum, 1873-1874; undated. (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Education (miscellaneous topics), 1870-1871. (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Education (miscellaneous topics), 1872-1873; undated. (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - General, 1869. (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - General, 1870. (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - General, 1870. (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - General, 1871. (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - General, 1872. (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - General, 1872. (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - General, 1873. (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - General, 1875-1877. (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - General, undated. (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Immigration, 1870-1871. (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Immigration, 1871. (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Immigration, 1871. (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Immigration, 1872. (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Immigration, 1872. (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Immigration, 1873. (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Institution for the Deaf, Dumb and Blind, Staunton, 1870-1872. (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Land scrip (college), 1869-1873. (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Locality officials (in reference to), 1870. (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Locality officials (in reference to), 1870. (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Protection and propagation of fish, 1871. (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Public schools, 1874. (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Registration books, 1872. (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - U.S. officials, 1869-1871. (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - U.S. officials, 1872-1873. (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College, 1872-1873. (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Visitors, Board of (University of Virginia), 1872. (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Oaths of Loyalty, State and Local Officials
    - Campbell - Carroll, 1870. (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Charlotte - Chesterfield, 1870. (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Clarke - Danville, 1870. (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Dinwiddie - Elizabeth City, 1870. (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Essex - Franklin, 1870. (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Frederick - Goochland, 1870. (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Grayson - Halifax, 1870. (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Hanover, 1870. (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Henrico - Highland, 1870. (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Isle of Wight - Lancaster, 1870. (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Lee - Loudoun, 1870. (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Louisa, 1870. (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Lunenburg - Lynchburg, 1870. (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Norfolk City, 1870. (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Norfolk City, 1870. (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Page - Patrick, 1870. (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Petersburg, 1870. (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Pittsylvania - Prince Edward, 1870. (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Prince George - Princess Anne, 1870. (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Pulaski, 1870. (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Richmond City, 1870. (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Richmond City, 1870. (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Richmond City, 1870. (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Rockbridge, 1870. (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Rockingham, 1870. (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Rockingham, 1870. (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Russell - Winchester, 1870. (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Opinions of the Attorney General
    - 1870. (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - 1871-1873; undated. (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Petitions for Pardons
    - 1869-1871. (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - 1871. (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - 1871. (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - 1871. (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - 1871. (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - 1871-1872. (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - 1872. (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - 1872. (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - 1872. (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - 1872. (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - 1872. (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - 1873. (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - 1873. (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - 1873-1875. (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Receipts
    - Issued to weigh master, 1870-1875. (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Recommendations, Appointment of Commissioners
    - Accomack - Bedford, 1870. (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Bland - Charlotte, 1870. (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Chesterfield - Fauquier, 1870. (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Floyd - Grayson, 1870. (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Greene - Isle of Wight, 1870. (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - James City - Lee, 1870. (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Loudoun - Middlesex, 1870. (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Montgomery - Nottoway, 1870. (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Orange - Prince Edward, 1870. (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Prince George - Richmond County, 1870. (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Roanoke - Surry, 1870. (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Sussex - York, 1870. (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Reports of the State Penitentiary
    - 1873. (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - 1873. (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - 1873. (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - 1873. (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - 1873. (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Resignations, Various Positions
    - 1870. (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - 1870; 1873. (Box 16, Folder 9)